Mary Gardiner Jones Papers
Mary Gardiner Jones Papers
1964-1984
Jones, Mary Gardiner, 1920-2009.
23.0 linear ft.
Papers of the U.S. Federal Trade Commissioner. Collection includes general and legal files, correspondence, speeches, and memorabilia.
149092
Biographical History
Mary Gardiner Jones (1920-2010) was a Federal Trade Commissioner and attorney. Her family had a long history of public service dating back to the 17th century, including her aunt, Rosalie Jones, who was a Senator's wife and suffragette, and the first woman lawyer to pass the District of Columbia bar exam.
Ms. Jones attended private schools and graduated from Wellesley College where she studied history and political science. She taught briefly at the George School (near Philadelphia) then in the 1940s joined the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), the precursor to the Central Intelligence Agency. In 1946 she entered Yale Law School, one of only two women in her class, where she was Law Journal editor and Order of the Coif. After graduation, her interest in policy issues and in international and antitrust law eventually led to a position with the Justice Department's Anti-Trust Division (1953-1960).
In 1960 she left to take a position as antitrust litigator with the New York law firm of Webster Sheffield, where she worked for four years. In 1964 the Johnson Administration, who under Johnson's leadership was actively recruiting talented women for various positions, was searching for a politically-neutral candidate for Federal Trade Commissioner and offered her the appointment. In an oral interview in 2003, Ms. Jones recalled her first months in office:
I knew the antitrust side. I didn't know anything about the consumer side. I learned the consumer side and then I developed an agenda. Being the only woman on the Commission, I was constantly invited by small consumer groups to speak. I wouldn't have known a consumer if I fell over one in those days, but I learned...
As she grew more comfortable in her role, Jones began to alter the focus of the FTC.
I suddenly realized that the purpose of the FTC up to that time had been to try and educate business as to what its responsibilities were...[and] I suddenly realized that what we needed was to have consumer supporters and to have them know what their rights were. We started to turn this around. We began to issue guidelines that talked to consumers about what their rights were and how they could exercise them.
Jones strove to get the FTC more involved in social justice issues, such as the higher prices and questionable marketing practices experienced by low-income inner-city consumers. During her tenure the Commission produced the Kerner Report, a study done just after, and partly in response to, the Watts Riots of 1965, which explored fraud, deceptive pricing, the resale of installment contracts, and other inner-city problems. The FTC also brought a series of cases in an attempt to address some of these practices that primarily affected the urban poor. She saw the FTC as "a very small, but significant tool to impact these larger issues." She also campaigned vigorously, and successfully, to get the FTC the power to impose sanctions on businesses rather than being limited to simple "cease and desist" orders. Two of the most useful sanctions were corrective advertising and ad substantiation (documentation of claims prior to using them in advertisements), both of which significantly strengthened the FTC's ability to act on the behalf of consumers.
Jones was a frequent and talented speechmaker for the FTC, capable of "throwing away" a speech in the middle of it if it wasn't working for her audience or for her purposes. Her speeches often concerned inner city problems but she was also deeply interested in the cultural and social impact of advertising on American society.
After leaving the FTC in 1973, Jones taught briefly at the University of Illinois' law and business schools. In 1975 she became vice president in charge of consumer affairs for Western Union, which brought her back to Washington, D.C. for seven years until she officially retired in 1982.
Recognizing the shift in consumer dissatisfaction from products (cars, clothing, false advertising) to services (health care, insurance services), she then founded the non-profit Consumer Interest Research Institute, which existed briefly before folding due to lack of funding. However, the Alliance for Public Technology, of which she was co-founder and president, throve in the technology-rich environment of the early 1980s, and still actively promotes consumer interest in telecommunications today (2007). In 1998 she became President of the Mental Health Association of D.C. where she instituted programs as diverse as children's services and mental health education for senior citizens in African-American churches.
Jones is the author of numerous articles and papers as well as 21st Century Learning and Health Care in the Home: Creating a National Telecommunications Network and the autobiographical Breaking Down Walls, One Woman's Triumph. In 2003 she received the Florence Kelley Consumer Leadership Award from the National Consumer's League for her efforts on behalf of consumers. She is also the recipient of distinguished service awards from the Society of Consumer Affairs Professionals, an honorary member of the American Home Economics Association, and was the Colston E. Warne Distinguished Lecturer at the Association of Consumer Interests (1992).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Mary Gardiner Jones Papers includes materials from her tenure as a Federal Trade Commissioner from 1964-1973. Material is arranged in eight series.
General files contains subject files on a variety of topics. Circulations consists of circulations produced by the FTC. Proposed upgraded ADP system contains material relating to the FTC's adoption of an automated reporting system in the late 1960s. Printed material consists of miscellaneous printed matter.
Correspondence includes official and personal; correspondents include government personnal (congressmen, the Federal Bar Association), professional organizations (American Association of University Women, American Political Science Association, National Council of Jewish Women, National Industrial Conference), media and marketing organizations (New York Times, Marketing Committee, National Association of Food Chains), academic institutions (Emory University, Northwestern University, Cornell Law School, Yale Law School), and individuals (David Buswell, Leon Sullivan, Don Wilmer). Companies represented in Legal files include American Cyanamid Company, Campbell Soup Company, Firestone Tire and Rubber, Standard Educators, and Zale Corporation.
Memorabilia contains awards and appointment books, scrapbooks, and an oral history. Writings contains speeches, opinions, articles, unidentified fragments, and a taped interview.
Other Formats Available
Audiocassettes of oral history have been digitized. Please contact the repository listed above for more information.
Separated Material
Copies of two books were found to be duplicates of items already in our holdings and were deacessioned. These were The Regulators: Watchdog Agencies and the Public Interest (1969) by Louis M. Kohlmeier, Jr. and Documents Illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States (1927) by the Government Printing Office.
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Politics, government and public administration; Activism and social reform; Jones, Mary Gardiner, 1920-2009.; Consumer protection -- United States.; United States. -- Federal Trade Commission -- Officials and employees.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1963-1969.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974.; Appointment books.; Audiocassettes.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Reports.; Speeches (documents)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Bulk of collection, gift of Mary Gardiner Jones, 1968-1973.
Binders of speeches and opinions, scrapbooks, oral history recording, gift of Charles Watkins, 2010.
Inventory
- General files
  - American Association of University Women
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Area Representative (Box 1)
    - I.C. Arts (Box 1)
    - Association Day, April 21, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Branch meeting
      - 1967 (Sep-Dec), 4 folders (Box 1)
      - 1968 (Jan-Jun, Sep-Dec), 10 folders (Box 1)
      - 1969 (Jan-Jun), 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Branch reports (Box 1)
    - Regional conference, 1966 (Box 1)
    - IC education (Box 1)
    - Emerging issues, 1970 (Box 1)
    - IC-Gap (Box 1)
    - General (Box 1)
    - Implementation chairmen, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Juvenile reports (Box 1)
    - Law and citizen committee, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Law and citizen program material, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - Legal comments (Box 1)
    - Meeting on programming for, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
    - Meeting times questionnaire (Box 1)
    - Membership (Box 1)
    - Newsletter (Box 1)
    - Notices regarding meetings (Box 1)
    - Pending reports (Box 1)
    - Possible speakers (Box 1)
    - Program chairman (Box 1)
    - Program chairmen (Box 1)
    - Program material (Box 1)
    - IC values (Box 1)
    - Speech, 15 Sep 1965 (Box 1)
    - Workshop on Urban Problems (Box 1)
  - American Home Economics Association
    - Dallas, Texas
      - Drafts and notes (Box 2)
      - Requests for speech (Box 2)
      - Completed speech (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Wisconsin material (Box 2)
  - American Home Products Corporation (Box 2)
  - American Motors Corporation (Box 2)
  - Appointments (Box 2)
  - Baum, Daniel J., binder containing typescript of paper, "Public participation in Federal Trade Commission Proceedings" (Box 25)
  - Beatrice Foods (Box 2)
  - Books requested by Mary Gardiner Jones (Box 2)
  - Boston College, 12 Apr 1966 (Box 2)
  - Brookings Institute (Box 2)
    - 1967-1969, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Helen Nelson (Box 2)
  - Canton Advertising Club (Box 2)
  - Carvel Corporation (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights Documentation Project
    - Dr. Vincent Brown (Box 2)
    - Judge J. Skelly Wright (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
  - Community Blood Bank of Kansas City Area (Box 2)
  - Conference
    - 17 Feb 1969 (Box 2)
    - 31 Oct 1969 (Box 2)
    - 2 Dec 1969 (Box 2)
    - 12 May 1970 (did not attend) (Box 2)
  - Consumer Protection Task Force (Box 2)
  - Core - real estate deceptions (Box 2)
  - Council on Community Affairs (Box 2)
  - D.C. Bar Association (Box 2)
  - Dean Foods Company (Box 2)
  - John Douglas (Box 2)
  - FBA-BNA Briefing (Box 2)
  - Georgetown visitation, 25 Apr 1967 (Box 2)
  - Great Books Group (Box 2)
  - Hatch Act (Box 2)
  - Howard University, 28 Apr 1966 (Box 2)
  - International Student Service (Box 2)
  - Interns (Box 2)
  - Interviews
    - FTC matters (Federal Trade Commission) (Box 2)
    - 9 Jan 1966 (Box 2)
    - 2 Mar 1971 (Box 2)
  - Kirkpatrick party, 28 Feb 1973 (Box 2)
  - Legal Aid (Box 3)
  - John V. Lindsay (Box 3)
  - McCrindle - real estate (Box 3)
  - Media, 11 Dec 1967 (Box 3)
  - Meeting
    - 8 Mar 1968 (Box 3)
    - 16 Mar 1970 (Box 3)
    - 16 Nov 1970 (Box 3)
  - Morgan Guaranty Survey (Box 3)
  - Nathan, Frederic (Box 3)
  - National Association of Food Chains, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Neighborhood Consumer Information Center (NCIC) (Box 3)
  - New York State Bar Association (Box 3)
  - North American Van Lines (Box 3)
  - Notes (Box 3)
  - Panels
    - 12 Jun 1968 (Box 3)
    - 25 Jun 1968 (Box 3)
    - 18 Feb 1969 (Box 3)
    - 12 Aug 1970 (Box 3)
  - Photo (Box 3)
  - Practicing Law Institute (Box 3)
  - Project Outreach (Box 3)
  - Rabb, Bruce (Box 3)
  - Radio Station WGMS (Box 3)
  - Reading Requests (Box 3)
  - Receipts (Box 3)
  - Rochester, New York (Box 3)
  - Sherman Act Commission (Box 3)
  - Southwest Legal Foundation, 16 Sep 1967
    - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Completed outline (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
  - Staff problems (Box 3)
  - Ibrahim B. Tejan (Box 3)
  - To Tell the Truth (Box 3)
  - Turner, Don (Box 3)
  - Visitors interviews (Box 3)
  - Montgomery Ward (Box 3)
  - Washington Ethical Society (Box 3)
  - Wellesley College
    - Alumnae magazine (Box 3)
    - Club (Box 4)
    - College 25th Union Gift Fund (Box 4)
  - White House Conference on Library and Information Services, 1979; printed vinyl case containing 3 audiocassette tapes and brochure for publication, "Dialogues on the future of library and information services" (Box 25)
  - White House staff recommendations (Box 4)
  - Work papers
    - Coca-Cola (Box 4)
    - General Foods (Box 4)
    - Grolier Inc. (Box 4)
    - Grove (Box 4)
    - Interstate Builders (Box 4)
    - National Dairy (Box 4)
    - Rodale Press (Box 4)
    - Spiegel, Inc. (Box 4)
    - State Credit Control Board, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Woman's World TV appearance, 2 Jun 1965 (Box 4)
- Circulations
  - Apr-Jun, 1967, 6 folders (Box 4)
    April 4-10, 12-28
    May 24-31
    Jun 1-20
  - Jun-Dec, 1967, 14 folders (Box 5)
    Jun 22-29
    Jul 1-31
    Aug 1-31
    Sep 1-30
    Oct 1-31
    Nov 1-30
    Dec 1-15
- Proposed upgraded ADP system
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Printed material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - U.S. Merger Cases, small binder with reprints from Congressional proceedings (Box 25)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Chronological file, 1969-1972; 14 folders (Box 6)
  - Reading file
    - Apr 1966- Sep 1967, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Oct 1967-Oct 1973, 12 folders (Box 7)
  - American Association of University Women (AAUW) (Box 7)
  - American Home Economics Association (Box 7)
  - American Management Association (Box 7)
  - American Political Science Association (Box 7)
  - American University (AU) (Box 7)
  - Baltimore, Maryland Chamber of Commerce (Box 7)
  - Book review (Box 7)
  - Buswell, David (Box 7)
  - Cigarettes (Box 7)
  - Civil Service Commission (Box 7)
  - Consumer
    - Committee (Box 7)
    - Complaints
      - General (Box 7)
      - 1964-1970, 5 folders (Box 7)
      - Public: Article Christian Science Monitor (Box 7)
    - Education (Box 7)
    - General correspondence (Box 7)
    - Luncheon (Box 8)
    - Mailing list (Box 8)
    - Research foundation (Box 8)
  - Congressmen, communications with (Box 8)
  - Cornell Law School (Box 8)
  - D.C. (District of Columbia) Bar Association (Box 8)
  - Emory University (Box 8)
  - Fan mail (Box 8)
  - Federal Bar Association (Box 8)
  - Field office (Box 8)
  - Georgetown University (Box 8)
  - International anti-trust speech (Box 8)
  - Invitations
    - Acceptances (Box 8)
    - Refusals, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Marketing committee (Box 8)
  - Media group (Box 8)
  - National Association of Food Chains (Box 8)
  - National Council of Jewish Women (Box 8)
  - National Industrial Conference (Box 8)
  - New attorneys - greetings (Box 8)
  - New York Times (Box 8)
  - Northwestern University (Box 8)
  - Office, 1967-1970; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Official
    - 1964-1970, 9 folders (Box 9)
    - 1970-1973, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Personal, 1964-1969; 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Personnel Club (Box 10)
  - Practicing Law Institute, 1965; 1970; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Referred to chairman (Box 10)
  - Referred to staff, 1968-1973; 8 folders (Box 11)
  - Rochester, New York (Box 11)
  - Request (Box 11)
  - San Francisco (Box 11)
  - Leon Sullivan (Box 11)
  - University of Southern California (Box 11)
  - Vanderbilt University (Box 11)
  - George Washington (Box 11)
  - Washington Wellesley (Box 11)
  - Wellesley College (Box 11)
  - Don Wilner (Box 11)
  - Women's Bar (Box 11)
  - Women's City Club (Box 11)
  - Yale Law School (Box 11)
  - Zonta Club of Washington (Box 11)
- Legal files
  - General
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - American Cyanamid Company (Box 12)
    - Burlington Industries (Box 12)
    - Campbell Soup Company (Box 12)
    - Crowell-Collier Publishing Company (Box 12)
    - Eastern Detective Academy Inc. (Box 12)
    - Firestone Tire and Rubber Company (Box 12)
    - Julius W. Hobson (Box 12)
    - LaSalle Extension University (Box 12)
    - Merit Distributing Company (Box 12)
    - New York Jewelry, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - The Portwood Company (Box 13)
    - Standard Educators, Inc. (Box 13)
    - Stanley Works (Box 13)
    - Star Office Supply Company, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Universe Chemicals, Inc. (Box 13)
    - Zale Corporation (Box 13)
  - American Bar Association (ABA)
    - Robinson-Patman, Los Angeles, California (Box 13)
  - Hearings
    - Williamsburg (notes) (Box 13)
    - House Subcommittee on Small Businesses and Robinson-Patman Act (Box 13)
  - Testimony
    - Kennedy Subcommittee (Box 13)
    - National Commission on Consumer Finance (Box 13)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards, 3 items (Box 13)
  - Appointment books, 1963-1972; 14 volumes (Box 13)
  - Oral history, jones_mg_001 through 006; 5 audiocassettes (Box 29)
  - Scrapbooks, 1964-1971; includes blue binder labeled "Miss Jones Personal," with letters of congratulation on her reappointment and carbons of her replies; 9 volumes (Box 26)
  - Scrapbooks, 1971-1973; 3 volumes (Box 28)
  - Scrapbooks, 1973-1984; 2 volumes (Box 27)
- Writings
  - Opinions, 1964-1973; red binders; 7 volumes (Box 25)
  - Speech lists and assortment (Box 14)
  - Speeches and articles
    - 1964 (Box 14)
    - 1964-1966, red binder (Box 27)
    - 1965, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - 1966, 13 folders (Box 14)
    - 1966-1967, red binder (Box 28)
    - 1967, 10 folders (Box 14, 15)
    - 1968, 45 folders (Box 15, 16)
    - 1968, red binder (Box 28)
    - 1969, 32 folders (Box 16-18)
    - 1969-1970, red binder (Box 28)
    - 1970, 29 folders (Box 19, 20)
    - 1970, red binder (Box 28)
    - 1971, 23 folders (Box 21, 22)
    - 1971, red binder (Box 27)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 23)
    - 1972-1973, red binder (Box 27)
    - 1975-1977, white binder (Box 29)
    - 1977 and unpublished, binder (Box 27)
    - 1979-1983, white binder (Box 29)
  - Fragments (Box 24)
  - Taped interview (Box 24)